<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>webgpu on My thought repository</title>
    <link>https://nelari.us/tags/webgpu/</link>
    <description>Recent content in webgpu on My thought repository</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 17:19:21 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nelari.us/tags/webgpu/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>GPU Pathtracer Devlog</title>
      <link>https://nelari.us/post/pathtracer_devlog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 17:19:21 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nelari.us/post/pathtracer_devlog/</guid>
      <description>This post is a devlog for my rayfinder project. Follow along to see the progress, starting from scratch by opening a simple window.
Adding atmospheric turbidity controls 2024-01-07
Commit: e0fe5f4
The updated sky model interpolates between the different sky and solar radiances at different atmospheric turbidities. A UI control is added to allow the selection of different turbidity values to see their effect on the image.
A turbidity of 1 corresponds to a very clear sky.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weekend raytracing with wgpu, part 2</title>
      <link>https://nelari.us/post/weekend_raytracing_with_wgpu_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 21:47:16 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nelari.us/post/weekend_raytracing_with_wgpu_2/</guid>
      <description>The first part of &amp;ldquo;Weekend raytracing with wgpu&amp;rdquo; left us with a basic implementation of Peter Shirley&amp;rsquo;s first book in the series of &amp;ldquo;Ray Tracing In One Weekend &amp;quot; books. &amp;ldquo;Ray Tracing: The Next Week&amp;rdquo; introduces additional features, such as texture support.
This post takes a look at adding a physically based sky model, in addition to adding textured material support. These features, combined, result in much nicer images than the basic renderer, without appreciably slowing down the renderer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weekend raytracing with wgpu, part 1</title>
      <link>https://nelari.us/post/weekend_raytracing_with_wgpu_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 06:43:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nelari.us/post/weekend_raytracing_with_wgpu_1/</guid>
      <description>Peter Shirley&amp;rsquo;s book Raytracing In One Weekend is a great way to kickstart your own path tracer. The book gives just enough information to get spheres rendered to your screen, minimizing the amount of time spent studying theory.
I wrote a straightforward implementation of the book’s renderer using Rust many years ago. Recently, I decided to go the extra mile and port the code to the GPU, using the wgpu crate.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
